A Finding Aid to the Fred Mitchell Papers, 1938-2007, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mitcfred
Archives of American Art
Fred Mitchell papers
1938-2007
AAA.mitcfred
Archives of American Art
14.3 Linear feet
The papers of Fred Mitchell, 1938-2007, measure 14.3 linear feet. Correspondence, writings, 29 diaries, and subject files, document his personal life and career as a painter and educator in New York City. The papers also include biographical materials, artwork, sketchbooks, printed material, and photographs.
Mitchell, Fred, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Fred Mitchell donated a small amount of printed material and photographs in 1972. The majority of the papers were donated in 2013 by Fred Pajerski, Fred Mitchell's nephew.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials,1942-circa 2005 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1947-2004 (Boxes 1-2; 1.9 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1940s-2004 (Boxes 2-3; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries, 1949-2002 (Boxes 4-6; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1943-2002 (Boxes 6-12; 6 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1940s-2002 (Boxes 12-13; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, 1955-1993 (Boxes 13, 15; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1938-2004 (Boxes 13-14; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, 1940s-2002 (Box 14; 0.5 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
Fred Mitchell (1923-2013), a painter and educator who worked in New York City, was among the first artists to open a studio in Coenties Slip on the East River in downtown Manhattan.
A native of Meridian, Mississippi, Madison Fred Mitchell (always called Fred), won a Scholastic Magazine award and his work was shown in its "15th Annual National High School Art Exhibit" held at the museum of the Carnegie Institute in 1942. Mitchell studied at the Carnegie Institute of Technology for a year before entering the U. S. Army. After World War II ended, he resumed his education at Cranbrook Academy of Art (BFA 1946 and MFA 1956). He moved to New York in 1951 and became a member of the "Downtown Group." In 1952 he was among the organizers of Tanager Gallery and in 1954 founded the Coenties Slip School of Art.
Mitchell enjoyed a long career as a highly regarded teacher of drawing, painting, and art history. He taught at Finch College, the Positano Art Workshop in Italy, and Cranbrook Academy in the 1950s. During the 1960s, he was affiliated with Downtown Art Center at Seamens Church Institute in Coenties Slip, New York University, Cornell University, and Ithaca College. In the early 1970s Mitchell taught at Queens College, and from the mid-1980s-early 2000s served on the faculties of Parsons School of Design, Art Students League of New York, and City University of New York's Kingsborough Community College in Brooklyn.
He exhibited widely in group shows and solo exhibitions in the New York area and throughout the United States. Among these venues were: Howard Wise Gallery, Meridian Museum, Munson-Williams-Proctor Art Institute, State University of New York Binghamton, University of Oregon, and Whitney Museum of American Art.
After several years of declining health, Fred Mitchell died in New York City in 2013.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Fred Mitchell, 1938-2007, measure 14.3 liner feet. Correspondence, writings, 29 diaries, and subject files document his personal life and career as a painter and educator in New York City. The papers also include biographical materials, artwork, sketchbooks, printed material, and photographs.
Among the biographical materials are biographical notes, military records, passports, and resumes. Correspondence includes both professional and personal letters. Correspondents include friends, former students, colleagues, and individuals of romantic interest.
Writings by Mitchell include notebooks containing names and addresses, appointments, lists and a variety of notes. Diaries record Mitchell's personal and professional activities, plans, aspirations, and memories; also, many volumes contain loose items such as printed material, drawings, notes and letters. Other authors represented are Harry Hope Reed, Peter Rooney, and Patrick Rucker.
Subject files maintained by Mitchell concern friends, teaching activities, exhibitions; also, interests in art, dance, poetry, and music. Files on the Mitchell family concern four generations and include Elizabeth Pajerski, his artist sister with whom he sometimes exhibited. There are files on Coenties Slip artists and related exhibitions. Other subjects of note are a Franz Kline traveling exhibition curated by Mitchell, and Mississippi Art Colony. Individuals for whom threre are substantial subject files include Justo Gonzales, James M. McQuade, Jim Ochman, Peter Rooney, John W. ("Dicky") Stevens, and Phil Sultz.
Most artwork is by Mitchell and consists mainly of drawings and sketches. Artwork by others includes drawings and watercolors by Peter Rooney, students, and unidentified artists. Mitchell's sketchbooks (16 volumes) contain sketches, drawings, and a few finished watercolors.
Printed material is about or mentions Mitchell. Included are a variety of items such as exhibition catalogs and announcements, brochures, clippings, press releases, and concert programs. Photographs are of Mitchell with family and friends; artwork by Mitchell and other artists; exhibition installations and openings; and places including the Wall-South neighborhood just before the destruction of his studio and travel pictures.
Gonzales, Justo; Kline, Franz, 1910-1962; McQuade, James M.; Mississippi Art Colony.; Ochman, Jim; Pajerski, Elizabeth; Reed, Harry Hope; Rooney, Peter; Rucker, Patrick; Stevens, Dick, 1928-; Sultz, Phil; Art--Study and teaching; Diaries; Drawings; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Watercolors
- Biographical Materials, 1942-circa 2005; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The folder titled "Awards and Certificates" contains a certificate of merit from Scholastic Magazine with a letter and copy of the issue containing an article about its "15th Annual National High School Art Exhibition" (1942) held at the Carnegie Institute. Also included is Mitchell's artist certification issued by New York City.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Address Books, undated; 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Addresses and Phone Numbers, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Astrological Chart by Peter, circa 1990s-circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1982; 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1990s-circa 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diplomas, 1942; 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Legal Documents, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Military Records, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Passports, Drivers License, Voter Registration, 1956-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Resumes, circa 1960s-circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1947-2004; Series 2; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence is professional and personal in nature, with incoming letters predominant. Correspondents include friends, former students, colleagues, and individuals of romantic interest. There are letters concerning exhibition and employment opportunities as well as routine personal business.
  Correspondence is arranged by year. A significant amount of additional correspondence is found in subject files. Some individual and institutional correspondents in this series may have subject files dedicated to them (Series 5), and loose letters are scattered throughout Mitchell's diaries (Series 4).
  - Correspondence, 1947-1960s; undated (Box 1, Folder 12-26)
  - Correspondence, 1970s-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1-20)
- Writings, circa 1940s-2004; Series 3; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Mitchell's writings include an article, notes, student papers, and a videocassette of his participation in an Art Students League panel discussion. Twenty six pocket notebooks contain names and addresses, appointments, lists, and notes (some notes are akin to brief diary entries). Writings by others include poems and an article. Of particular interest is Peter Rooney's unpublished Fred Mitchell catalogue raisonne with notes.
  Writings by Mitchell are arranged by record type and filed alphabetically by folder title. Writings by others are alphabetized by author.
  - By Mitchell (Box 3)
    - Article, "Design in America: The Cranbrook Vision 1925-1950" in American Craft, vol. 44, no. 2, 1984 April - 1984 May (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-19)
    - Notes, undated; 1969-1999 (Box 3, Folder 20-34)
    - Notes, Renaissance to 19th Century Course, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Notes from Trips, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Notes, Sojourning, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Notebooks, 1963-2004 (Box 3, Folder 38-41)
    - Panel Discussion, Art Students League Forum, Raw and Upfront, "How Artists Happen", 1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Student Papers, circa 1940s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - By Others (Box 4)
    - Louderson and Unidentified Authors. Poems, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reed, Harry Hope. Brochure for NYC Bicycle Tour sponsored by Friends of the Parks, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Rooney, Peter. Fred Mitchell Catalogue Raisonné with Notes, 1994-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Rucker, Patrick. "Reflections on the Helican Festival at Weill Hall", 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Diaries, 1949-2002; Series 4; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Diaries (29 volumes) record Mitchell's personal and professional activities, plans, aspirations, and memories. Entries range from extremely brief notes to lengthy, substantial reflections on the day's events. Most volumes contain drawings and sketches; many also include loose items such as clippings, letters, notes, drawings, and printed material. Sometimes coins are attached, accompanied by a personal memory relating to the coin's date. A substantial number of diary entries were recorded on loose sheets of paper.
  Volumes are numbered and arranged chronologically. Several volumes contain overlapping dates; some record multiple years, and some years fill more than a single volume. Entries on loose pages, also arranged by year, follow volume 29.
  - Volume 1, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Volume 2, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Volume 3, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Volume 4, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Volume 5, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Volume 6, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Volume 7, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Volume 8, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Volume 9, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Volume 10, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Volume 11, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Volume 12, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Volume 13, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Volume 14, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Volume 15, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Volume 16, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Volume 17, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Volume 18, 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Volume 19, 1989-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Volume 20, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Volume 21, 1991-1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Volume 22, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Volume 23, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Volume 24, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Volume 25, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Volume 26, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Volume 27, 1994-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Volume 28, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Volume 29, 1997-2002 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Diary Entries on Loose Pages, undated; 1969-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4-19)
- Subject Files, 1943-2007; Series 5; 6 Linear feet Boxes 6-12
  Subject files contain varying combinations of correspondence, printed material, writings, art work and photographs that document Mitchell's family, friendships, exhibitions, teaching, and his interests in art, dance, poetry, and music. Individuals for whom there are substatial subject files include: Justo Gonzales, James M. McQuade, Jim Ochman, Peter Rooney, John W. ("Dicky") Stevens, and Phil Sultz.
  This series is alphabetized by file title.
  - 128 Front Street, New York City, circa 1952-circa 1967 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Agostini, Peter, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1984-1993 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Anatomy, Human, circa 1950s-1994 (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
  - Anderson, Walter, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Animals and Birds, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - The Arkansas Arts Center, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Arnold, Bruce ("Brucerino"), 1980s (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - The Armillary Sphere, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Art and Artists of Mississippi, 1790-1980, the first volume in "The New Mississippi Heritage Series" to be published in 1998, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Art Awards, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - The Art Students League, undated; 1975-2004 (Box 6, Folder 32-34)
  - Artz, Tony, "Woman of Change", undated; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ashbury, John, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Aspen School of Contemporary Art and Aspen Art Gallery, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Auction Debacle, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Augusta, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Barcroft, George, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Barron, Alton, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Becker, Boris, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Battcock, Gregory, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Beauchamp, Bob, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Benca, Adolf, 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Bialski, David, 1983-1994 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Birthdays and Anniversaries, undated; 1995 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Bohary, Jim, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Brask, Ole, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Bronson, Duane, 1979-1988 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Bronxville, "Drawings and Paintings: Southern Tipping, Coenties Slipping" (1999 September 17-1979 October 22) (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "Brother-Sister Exhibit, Fred Mitchell and Elizabeth Pajerski," Marie Hull Gallery, Hinds Junior College, Raymond, Mississippi (1979) (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Buddhism, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Bueckner & Harpsichords, 1972-1982 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Burton, Fred, "Freddie B the postcard king", undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cage, John, 1982-1992 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Cape Cod -- Provincetown Art Association and Museum; Castle Hill, Truro Center for the Arts, undated; 1990-1996 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - "Capturing Meridian", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Coenties Slip, 1974-1990s (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Coenties Slip Artists, 1958-1996 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Coenties Slip Exhibition, Buecher & Harpsichords (1973 January -- 1973 February) (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Coenties Slip Studio, 1955-1976 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Columbia University, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Congregation Beth Elohim Art Exhibition and Sale, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Cornell University, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Cranbrook Academy of Art/ The Cranbrook Educational Community, 1965-1994; undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Crellin, John ("Giovanni"), 1981-1992 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Merce Cunningham Dance Company, 1970-1994 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Dalai Lama, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Dali, Salvadore, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Dance, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Dawson, Bess, The Summit Studio, Gulf South Gallery, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - De Lallier, Alex, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Delaware Art Museum, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Dickerman, Henry E., 1960 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Doughty, Thomas, South Branch of the Potomac, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Downtown Art Center, circa 1960s-1975 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Dunn, Douglas, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - The Eden Isle Art Colony, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Elrick, Marc and Glenn Lanteigne, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Enrico, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Exhibitions, Lower East Side, 1980s (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Family (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, James Milton (nephew), undated; 1960s-1992 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Mitchell, Thomas Lyle (brother) and Marie Mitchell, undated; 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Mitchell, Thomas Lyle, Jr. (nephew), undated; 1960s-1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Pajerski, Elizabeth Mitchell (sister) and Frank Pajerski, undated; 1950-2000 (Box 8, Folder 6-16)
    - Pajerski, Fred Mitchell (nephew), undated; 1960s-1992 (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Fellah, Serge, circa 1990s (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Figures, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - "Four Abstract Artists: Recent Works by John Loy, James McDermid, Fred Mitchell, Easton Pribble," The Central New York Arts Commission Gallery, Utica, NY (1992), 1991 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - "Four Painters: Bohary, Engleson, Passlat, Rich" (1976 November) (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "Four Viewpoints," Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute School of Art (1977 November 9 -- 1977 November 23) (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Friends' Exhibitions, Visual and Athletic, undated; 1980s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Fundació Antoni Tapies, 1990s (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Gallery X, 1998-2000 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Garabedian, Robert, 1976-1981 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - "The Gathering of the Avant-Garde: The Lower East Side, 1948-1970" (1985) (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Gonzales, Justo, 1983-1993; undated (Box 8, Folder 29-33)
  - Gonzalez, Justo, and Giving Out my Books, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Adolph and Esther Gottlieb Foundation, Inc., 1989-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Grant Possibilities, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Greater Lafayette Museum of Art, Lafayette, Indiana, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Greene, Johnny, 1968-1992 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Greig, Dudley B., 1964-1991; undated (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Gros, Nancy, 1958-1961; undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Gruder, Beth, 1966-1987 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Solomon R. Guggenheim Musuem, "Younger American Painters" (1954-1955), 1954-1962 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Guyton, Jeff, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Hale, Robert Beverly, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Hamilton, William ("Bimbo Tomasso"), 1970s-1986 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Haring, Keith, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Hartley, Marsden, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Heilman, Philip, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Heliker, Jack, 1970s-1980 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Hoenig, Adele ("Adelina"), 1980s (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Hofmann, Hans, 1980s (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Hopson, Allan, 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Hughes, Robert, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Hunterdon Art Center, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Ippolito, Angelo, 1968-1992 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Italy, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Ithaca College, 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Jessup, Andy, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Job Applications, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Job Possibilities, 1960s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Johnson, Meryl, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Judson Memorial Church Centennial, 1986-1990 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Kearchler, Tom, 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Kelly, Ellsworth, 1981-2003 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Kingsborough Community College (Box 9)
    - Kingsborough Community College, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - New Course, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Painting Course, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Spring 1995 Crisis, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Student Papers, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Watercolor Course, 1988-2001 (Box 9, Folder 37-42)
    - College Art Gallery, "Fred Mitchell Paintings" (1987 February 4-1987 February 23) (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - College Art Gallery, "Painting in Watercolor" (1992 December 2 -- 1993 January 5) (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Franz Kline Show (Box 9)
    - Administrative Matters, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Catalogue, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - "Franz Kline: The Early Works as Signals," University Art Gallery, SUNY Binghamton (1977 March 14 -- 1977 April 18) (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Lecture, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Loans, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - My Writings and Notes, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Neuberger Museum, SUNY Purchase (1977) (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Notes, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Possibilities and Plans, 1970s (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Research, 1970s (Binder 9, Folder 55)
    - Sordoni Art Gallery, Wilkes College, Wilkes-Barre, PA (1978 August 18 - 1978 September 10), 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - University of Iowa Proposal for Retropsective Exhibition, circa 1980s (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Landmark Gallery Exhibition "Fred Mitchell" (1982 January 9 -- 1982 February 3), 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Lattimore, Richmond, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Lee, Harry, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Leger, Fernand, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Loans, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Low, Terry, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "The Magic Circle," The Bronx Museum of the Arts (1977), 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Malevich, Kazimir, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Marceau, Marcel, 1973-1992 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Markey Mark, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Manguet, Albert, undated; 1985 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Marshall, John, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - McCabe, Tommy ("Tomassino"), 1980s-1990s (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - McCauley, Billy Ray, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - McLellan, Alden and Family, undated; 1992 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - McNeil, George, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - McQuade, James M., 1970s-1990 (Box 10, Folder 17-18)
  - Meridian Community College Exhibition, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Meridian Museum of Art, 1972-1988 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Missing Paintings and Objects, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Missing Tryptich, Middy the Juggler, 1993-1994 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Mississippi, undated; 1960s-1990s (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Mississippi Art Colony, 1960s-1990s; Includes 1 videocassette: VHS (Box 10, Folder 24-25)
  - Mississippi Museum of Art, Jackson, undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Missouri Exhibitions, 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - "Modernism into Abstraction: Fred Mitchell, 1940-1949" (2007 March) (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Moore, Frank, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Moore, Tom and Meridian, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Mosaics, 1956; undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Motherwell, Robert, 1978-1994; undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute of Art, 1990-2003; undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor School of Art, Visiting Artist, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Nevelson, Louise, circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - New Places and Needs, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - The New York School, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - New York University, 1963-1975 (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Newman, Annalee, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - "Nine Artists/Coenties Slip," Whitney Museum of American Art (1974) (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Normal, Craig, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Ochman, Jim, 1978-1983; undated (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
  - Okada, Frank, 1963-2000; undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Oregon Friends, 1985; undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Outdoor Color Drawing Class, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Pace Gallery, 1991-1993 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Pace, Stephen, 1970s-2002 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Painting Trip, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Passlof, Pat, circa 1970s (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Pederson, Allen, 1977-1987 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Pederson-Krag, Gillian, undated; 1970s-1983 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Petrochi, Lello, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Pets -- Gwendolyn's Family,Vernoica, Euripidosia, Billy Budd, and Nikko-San, undated; 1984-1984 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Pfriem, Bernard, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Piper, John, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Poets, undated; 1994 (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Poleski, Stephen, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Positano, Sigmund, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - Prefontaine, Steve, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Pribble, Easton, 1974-2001; undated (Box 10, Folder 61)